She has disappeared too.
Ona też zniknęła.
Mei?
Mei?
Are you sure she isn't hiding? She likes making bad jokes.
Może się schowała? Lubi kiepskie żarty.
She is gone.
Zniknęła.
It's the same with Mao.
Tak samo jak Mao.
Sarina.
Sarina.
What Mei said earlier...
Mei powiedziała...
Sarina!
Sarina!
Explain yourself, class representative!
Tłumacz się, przewodnicząca!
-Yes! -What did Mei say?
- Tak! - Co powiedziała Mei?
She said we're all the same.
Że jesteśmy takie same.
What?
Co?
We all bullied Miho!
Dręczyłyśmy Miho!
-Don't change the subject! -You heard Mei!
- Nie zmieniaj tematu! - Słyszałaś Mei!
-She said you did it! -Explain that!
- Powiedziała, że to ty! - Wytłumacz się!
Hold on!
Zaraz!
I just thought that Mei was doing her usual thing.
Myślałam, że to klasyczne dziwne zachowanie Mei.
-You are defending her? -That's not what I mean,
- Bronisz jej? - Nie o to mi chodzi.
but whenever there is trouble,
Ale kiedy jest jakiś problem,
Mei always makes a fuss and says, "It's not my fault!"
Mei zawsze mówi, że to nie jej wina.
So what?
No i?
Why would she mention Sarina now?
Czemu wspomniała o Sarinie?
You shouldn't hide things.
Nie powinnaś niczego ukrywać.
Shouldn't Mana and Memi be the ones confessing?
To Mana i Memi powinny się tłumaczyć.
-What? -Why us?
- Co? - Dlaczego my?
Come on, everyone. Let's all just calm down.
Uspokójmy się wszystkie.
You are right.
Racja.
Then,
Dobrze,
I'll summarize everything.
podsumujmy.
Who was the first to bully Miho?
Kto pierwszy znęcał się nad Miho?
I think it was Mao.
Chyba Mao.
What is wrong?
Co się stało?
I have always thought
Zawsze myślałam...
that there was something between her and Miho.
że coś między nimi było.
Who threw away her books?
Kto wyrzucił jej książki?
It was Mao.
Mao.
Who cut her skirt?
Kto pociął jej spódniczkę?
You mean Sarina?
Sarina?
So...
Więc...
-We have to make her confess. -Will that save us?
- Musi się przyznać. - Myślisz, że to nas ocali?
-We're blaming people who aren't here. -Shiho is more to blame than us.
- Oskarżamy te, których nie ma. - Shiho była gorsza niż my.
That's right. You did stuff when you could still talk.
To prawda. Kiedy jeszcze mówiłaś, byłaś paskudna.
You lost your voice about three months ago, right?
Straciłaś głos trzy miesiące temu, prawda?
That's about the same time Miho vanished.
To mniej więcej... Wtedy, kiedy zaginęła Miho.
Yes! I noticed too!
Tak! Też to zauważyłam!
You can still talk, right?
Możesz mówić, prawda?
This is fishy. She is hiding something.
To podejrzane. Ona coś ukrywa.
Quit blaming or suspecting other people!
Przestańcie obwiniać i podejrzewać innych!
Why?
Dlaczego?
Isn't that our only way out of here?
Chyba tylko tak stąd wyjdziemy.
Confess, someone! I don't care who!
Niech ktoś się przyzna!
I didn't do it!
Ja nic nie zrobiłam!
It's you two!
To wy dwie!
No! It was Mao and Shiho!
Nie, to Mao i Shiho!
Anyone else? What about you, Kage?
Ktoś jeszcze? Kage?
Are you listening?
Słuchasz nas?
No, don't come here!
Nie, nie podchodź!
What is going on?
Co jest?
-Monsters! -What?
- Potwory! - Co?
-There are monsters! -Where?
- Gdzie?
On the table!
Na stole!
No!
Nie!
Mirei?
Mirei!
Let's always
Trzymajmy się
stick together!
razem!
Come to think of it,
Przypomniałam sobie,
people messed with her bag too.
że było też coś z jej plecakiem.
Cut it out!
Przestań!
We have to remember about Miho, right?
Musimy pamiętać o Miho, prawda?
That was Mao too.
To wina Mao.
What did she do?
Co zrobiła?
-What? -Well,
- Co? - Włożyła jej do plecaka
she put some stuff inside to frighten her.
jakieś rzeczy, by ją przestraszyć.
To frighten her?
Przestraszyć?
Yes, like mice.
Tak. Na przykład myszy.
They were toys, not like the real ones earlier.
To były zabawki, nie prawdziwe myszy.
Shut up!
Zamknij się!
You asked.
Pytałaś.
Is something happening up there?
Coś tam się dzieje?
-No! -Back! Stay back!
- Nie! - Odsuń się!
-That's a frog! -I know!
- To żaba! - Wiem!
Remember when Miho fell down the library stairs?
Pamiętacie, jak Miho spadła ze schodów?
The fall that put her in the wheelchair?
Ten upadek, przez który wylądowała na wózku?
I didn't tell anyone, but I think it was Mei who did that.
Nikomu nie mówiłam, ale myślę, że to była sprawka Mei.
Yes, she seemed really suspicious.
Tak, wydawała się podejrzana.
She had an accomplice.
Miała wspólnika.
I heard the teachers talking about it once.
Słyszałam, jak nauczyciele o tym mówili.
They found a toy frog there.
Znaleźli tam zabawkową żabę.
A frog?
Żabę?
Everything that is happening here is a message from Miho.
To wszystko wiadomości od Miho.
All of it. The mice, and those frogs.
Wszystko. Myszy i żaby.
Yuck!
Fuj!
They are all messages from Miho!
To wiadomości od Miho!
All the stuff on the walls too.
Rzeczy na ścianach też.
It's like a library.
To jakby biblioteka.
Miho fell down the library stairs.
Tam Miho spadła ze schodów.
It's a message from Miho?
To wiadomość od Miho?
Oh, and there's this.
No i to.
I have been wondering what this is.
Zastanawiałam się nad ich znaczeniem.
These leg irons?
Tych kajdan?
With this, we can't stand or walk around.
Nie możemy wstać ani chodzić.
Oh!
Och!
Miho is after whoever got her legs disabled.
Miho chce dopaść tę, przez którą jest na wózku.
But who is that?
Ale która to?
The biggest liar in this room.
Największa kłamczucha w pokoju.
I'll roast her.
Zniszczę ją.
That seems awful.
Brzmi strasznie.
Don't you want to get out of here?
Chcesz stąd wyjść?
Then shut up and do as I say!
To zamknij się i mnie słuchaj!
They're not poisonous.
Nie są trujące.
Sarina.
Sarina.
Sorry. I dropped a frog.
Wybacz, upuściłam żabę.
Give me your phone.
Daj mi swój telefon.
Why? What is wrong?
Czemu? Co się stało?
We want to know if you are a liar.
Chcemy sprawdzić, czy kłamiesz.
What do you mean?
Co masz na myśli?
Your Line chat history!
Historia wiadomości z komunikatora.
After that accident,
Po wypadku,
when Miho's legs got disabled,
kiedy Miho straciła władzę w nogach,
I know Mei sent you a message, Sarina.
Mei wysłała ci wiadomość.
I mean, she even said that earlier,
Powiedziała wcześniej,
"It's not my fault. It was Sarina who did it."
że to nie jej wina, tylko twoja.
She must have sent you a message.
Musiała do ciebie napisać.
That's what Mei would do.
To w stylu Mei.
Give it to me!
Daj mi go!
You will do it if you are innocent!
Zrobisz to, jeśli jesteś niewinna!
I'll only show Mirei.
Pokażę tylko Mirei.
What?
Co?
You can't do that.
Nie możesz.
Why me?
Dlaczego mi?
That may be a good idea.
To może być dobry pomysł.
What? But...
Co? Ale...
Mirei, we will know if you are lying.
Będziemy wiedziały, jeśli skłamiesz.
I'm sure Miho is watching from somewhere.
Miho na pewno nas obserwuje.
Cover for each other. I know you are both responsible.
Kryjecie siebie nawzajem, bo to wasza wina.
You are responsible too, Mirei!
Twoja też, Mirei!
Mirei.
Mirei.
Sarina.
Sarina.
I...
Ja...
can't tell a lie.
nie umiem kłamać.
That's okay. I know that.
W porządku, wiem o tym.
I can't tell a lie.
Nie umiem kłamać.
You don't mind?
Odpowiada ci to?
I know. It's okay.
Tak, nie martw się.
In that case, show everyone.
To pokaż wszystkim.
I mean,
Rozumiesz...
there's no way I can lie!
że naprawdę nie potrafię kłamać?
Hold on. You suspect me?
Co? Podejrzewasz mnie?
I swear I haven't done anything!
Przyrzekam, że nic nie zrobiłam!
Believe me!
Uwierz mi!
When spring comes, we will be at the same university, right?
Wiosną będziemy na tej samej uczelni, prawda?
Just admit that you are guilty.
Przyznaj się do winy.
I want to save us all too!
Ja też chcę nas uratować!
If you did it, say it!
Jeśli to zrobiłaś, przyznaj się!
What? Why won't you believe me?
Co? Dlaczego mi nie wierzysz?
Don't get me involved!
Nie mieszaj mnie w to!
Sarina! Apologize right now!
Sarina! Natychmiast przeproś!
Shut up!
Zamknij się!
You see, I know
Kyoko, wiem...
what you did to Miho, Kyoko.
co zrobiłaś Miho.
You broke a bottle near Miho, right?
Rozbiłaś butelkę, prawda?
You were going to cut her face with it, right?
Chciałaś jej pociąć twarz, prawda?
No, I wasn't.
Nie.
What?
Co?
The bell is ringing again!
Znowu dzwoni!
No! Why?
Nie! Dlaczego?
I knew it.
Wiedziałam.
It's Sarina's turn.
To kolej Sariny.
No! Why? I didn't do anything!
Nie! Dlaczego? Nic nie zrobiłam!
Apologize! Apologize to Miho right this second!
W tej chwili przeproś Miho!
I never meant it to happen!
Nie chciałam tego!
Did you push her down the stairs? Or didn't you?
Zrzuciłaś ją ze schodów czy nie?
I just wanted to scare her a little!
Chciałam ją tylko wystraszyć!
I never thought she would get badly hurt.
Nie sądziłam, że stanie się jej krzywda!
Enough! Apologize right now!
Dość tego! Przeproś!
It's not my fault!
To nie moja wina!
Miho fell on her own!
Miho sama spadła!
She fell down the stairs on purpose!
Specjalnie spadła ze schodów!
I saw her!
Widziałam to!
Apologize!
Przeproś!
You will save everyone!
Uratujesz nas!
Believe me!
Uwierzcie mi!
Please believe me!
Błagam!
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
Damn you, Miho!
Niech cię szlag, Miho!
It's all your fault!
To twoja wina!
Check your feet!
Sprawdźcie stopy!
Hey! They broke their promise!
Hej! Złamali obietnicę!
What is going on? Sarina apologized!
O co chodzi? Sarina przeprosiła!
It wasn't our fault.
To nie nasza wina.
Where is the key?
Gdzie klucz?
Where did it go?
Zniknął?
It's not here.
Tu go nie ma.
Are you kidding me?
To jakiś żart?
Hey, I thought we would be released if we found out who disabled her legs.
Myślałam, że nas wypuszczą, kiedy odkryjemy, kto skrzywdził Miho.
They promised!
Obiecali!
They probably never intended to let us go.
Pewnie nigdy nie planowali nas uwalniać.
Cut that out!
Przestań!
Are we going to disappear one by one?
Znikniemy jedna po drugiej?
I can't take this!
Nie wytrzymam!
Enough of that! Look for the key!
Dość tego! Szukajcie klucza!
-What's that? -No!
- Co to? - Nie!
What is it?
Co to?
-What's it? -No!
- Co to jest? - Nie!
What is it?
Co to?
-I'm scared. -What's it?
- Boję się. - Co to?
-What is this? -I'm scared.
- Co to jest? - Boję się.
What is this?
Co to jest?
-What's this? -I think it's oil.
- Co to? - Chyba olej.
Why is that dripping down?
Czemu ścieka z sufitu?
Can we ignore it?
Możemy go zignorować?
How can we stop it?
Jak to zatrzymać?
Hey.
Hej.
Why don't we just burn everything?
Może po prostu wszystko spalimy?
What?
Co?
Let's set this room on fire and burn the whole thing.
Podpalmy ten pokój i spalmy wszystko.
We will die too!
Umrzemy!
Are you crazy?
Zwariowałaś?
Of course not.
Nie.
Don't burn this place.
Nie możemy tego spalić.
It might be a good idea to set a fire.
Pożar może być dobrym pomysłem.
What is wrong with you, Mana?
Zwariowałaś, Mana?
A fire truck will come if we create a fire.
Straż pożarna nas uwolni.
We will die before that happens.
Umrzemy, zanim przyjedzie.
If we don't do something desperate, we will die one by one.
Jeśli nie zrobimy nic, umrzemy jedna po drugiej.
Don't say that!
Nie mów tak!
I'm serious.
Mówię poważnie.
Let's light this place on fire
Podpalmy to miejsce...
and bet all our hopes on that.
i liczmy na cud.
There is no fire around here.
Nie ma tu żadnego ognia.
I have a lighter.
Mam zapalniczkę.
I was coming home from work.
Wracałam z pracy.
Work?
Z pracy?
What is your job?
Gdzie pracujesz?
Forget about that.
To nie ma znaczenia.
Today is our graduation day.
Dzisiaj kończymy szkołę.
Cut that out!
Przestań!
Don't do it!
Nie rób tego!
There are candles over there too.
Tam są świece.
Really?
Naprawdę?
Get one of those candles.
Weź jedną z nich.
I'm against this.
Nie popieram tego.
Come on, Memi!
Przestań, Memi!
I don't want to die.
Nie chcę umierać.
-We will die anyway. -Cut it out!
- I tak umrzemy. - Przestań!
Memi!
Memi!
I don't want to die by fire!
Nie chcę spłonąć!
Ayaka! What are you doing?
Ayaka! Co ty robisz?
We don't need one. We can just knock one over.
Nie potrzebujemy świec. Wystarczy, że jedną przewrócimy.
Stop it!
Przestań!
-Let go! -Calm down!
- Puść mnie! - Uspokój się!
-I can't take this! -Stop it, you guys!
- Nie wytrzymam! - Przestańcie!
Don't come up here.
Nie zbliżaj się.
-Ayaka! -Let go of me!
- Ayaka! - Puść mnie!
So, it's like this?
Więc to tak?
Do what you like.
Rób, co chcesz.
You are fucking crazy.
Pieprzona wariatka.
What the hell is this?
Co to ma być?
We're losing our minds.
Tracimy rozum.
actually serious, are you?
nie mówisz poważnie, prawda?
"MIRAI E" BY KIRORO
KIRORO – „MIRAI E”
I have heard this before.
Znam to.
It's the song Class One sang together at last year's School Festival.
Pierwsza klasa śpiewała to na szkolnym festiwalu w zeszłym roku.
Oh, yes.
Faktycznie.
I really liked that.
Bardzo mi się podobało.
I have always enjoyed it.
Lubię tę piosenkę.
I always listen to it when I'm feeling down.
Słucham jej, kiedy mi smutno.
Like the time when Miho did something mean to you?
Na przykład wtedy, kiedy Miho jest wredna?
Miho, forgive everyone.
Wybacz nam, Miho.
Hey.
Hej.
Mirei.
Mirei.
Everyone is doing their own thing.
Każda robi coś innego.
This is crazy! Why is oil dripping from the ceiling?
To jakieś wariactwo! Czemu ten olej kapie z sufitu?
This must be like the frogs! It's a message from Miho!
To pewnie coś takiego, jak te żaby, wiadomość od Miho!
Are you even listening, Shiho?
Słuchasz mnie, Shiho?
We were busy with exams, but we were worried about you.
Byłyśmy zajęte egzaminami, ale martwiłyśmy się o ciebie.
We wondered what happened to you, but you never texted us back or anything!
Zastanawiałyśmy się, co ci się stało, ale nigdy nam nie odpisałaś!
What happened to you?
Co ci się stało?
Why can't you talk?
Dlaczego nie mówisz?
Tell us, will you?
Powiesz nam?
What?
Co?
Look at this?
Mam spojrzeć?
You mean
Bateria...
your battery is dead?
ci padła?
Then, do you want to use mine?
Chcesz użyć mojego?
It's not Miho.
To nie Miho.
What?
Co?
The culprit
Miho...
is not Miho.
nie jest sprawcą.
"The culprit
„Miho...
is not Miho."
nie jest sprawcą”.
Okay,
Dobrze,
let's begin.
zaczynajmy.
-Ready... -The culprit
- Gotowe... - Miho
is not Miho.
nie jest sprawcą.
The culprit is not Miho.
Miho nie jest sprawcą.
Shiho?
Shiho?
Listen to what Shiho has to say, okay?
Posłuchajcie Shiho, dobrze?
What?
Co?
The culprit is not Miho.
Miho nie jest sprawcą.
It must be someone else.
To musi być ktoś inny.
It's too late for that.
Za późno na to.
If it's not Miho, then why bring us here?
Jeśli to nie Miho, to kto nas tu ściągnął?
Aren't we here because we bullied Miho?
Przecież dręczyłyśmy Miho.
At the School Festival,
Podczas szkolnego festiwalu...
the lacrosse team spilled oil.
drużyna lacrosse’a wylała olej.
Hold on. I don't understand.
Zaraz, nie rozumiem.
What are you talking about?
O czym ty mówisz?
Shiho, I'll tell everyone.
Shiho, ja im powiem.
Do you remember how the lacrosse team got severely punished
Pamiętacie, jak drużyna lacrosse’a dostała karę
at the school festival?
na szkolnym festiwalu?
They had a donut booth,
Mieli budkę z pączkami,
but they spilled the oil they were going to use.
ale wylali olej, którego mieli użyć.
They spilled it all.
Wylali cały.
Right.
Faktycznie.
The teacher said that it wasn't handled properly.
Nauczyciel powiedział, że to wina uczniów.
You didn't handle it properly.
To twoja wina.
You let students from other schools into the team room.
Wpuściłaś uczniów z innych szkół do naszej sali.
This oil is
Ten olej
a message telling us
to wiadomość dla nas,
to remember that accident.
żebyśmy przypomniały sobie o tym wypadku.
But that accident...
Ale ten wypadek...
Wasn't that part of that?
To nie była część tego?
That? You mean "that"?
Masz na myśli „to”?
You are right.
Masz rację.
I remember seeing that then.
Widziałam to wtedy.
If that's it, then the culprit...
Skoro tak, sprawcą jest...
What?
Co?
PERFECT JUSTICE HAS TWEETED
IDEALNA SPRAWIEDLIWOŚĆ DODAŁA NOWEGO TWEETA
How did this happen?
Jak to się stało?
THIS DRAMA IS A WORK OF FICTION.
PRZEDSTAWIONY SERIAL JEST FIKCJĄ.
Subtitle translation by Brian Athey
Napisy: Arianna Sugier